<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The trumpet of the Lord blowne. Or, a blast against pride and oppression, and the defiled liberty, which stands in the flesh. By a servant and messenger of the Lord, who is called into the work of the Lord, and to blow his trumpet in England; so that all may be forwarned in this day of the Lords calm, and be left without excuse, and in the day of his righteous judgments be found just and true; in love to all imprisoned souls. / By a lover of all souls, who is called, James Parnel.</title>
            <author>Parnell, James, 1637?-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91472</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P539</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E830_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207433</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866482</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866482</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168077</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91472)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168077)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 126:E830[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The trumpet of the Lord blowne. Or, a blast against pride and oppression, and the defiled liberty, which stands in the flesh. By a servant and messenger of the Lord, who is called into the work of the Lord, and to blow his trumpet in England; so that all may be forwarned in this day of the Lords calm, and be left without excuse, and in the day of his righteous judgments be found just and true; in love to all imprisoned souls. / By a lover of all souls, who is called, James Parnel.</title>
                  <author>Parnell, James, 1637?-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at the Black Spread Eagle, neer the west end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 12. 1654"; 5 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168077:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TRVMPET OF THE LORD BLOWNE. <hi>OR,</hi> A BLAST Againſt Pride and Oppreſſion, and the Defiled Liberty, which ſtands in the Fleſh.</p>
            <p>By a Servant and Meſsenger of the Lord, who is called into the work of the Lord, and to blow his Trumpet in England; ſo that all may be fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned in this day of the Lords calm, and be left without excuſe, and in the day of his righteous Judgments be found juſt and true; in love to all impriſoned Souls.</p>
            <p>By a Lover of all Souls, who is called, <hi>JAMES PARNEL.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Black Spread Eagle, neer the weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:168077:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168077:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> TRUMPET of the Lord blown.</head>
            <p>WOE unto you that are called Lords, Ladies, Knights, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, and Gentlewomen, in reſpect to your perſons, who are exalted in the earth, who are proud, and high, and lofty, who are called of men Maſter, and Sir, and Miſtris, and Madam, in reſpect to your perſons, becauſe of your gay Cloathing, becauſe of your much earth, which by fraud, deceit, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion you have gotten together, you are exalted above your fellow-creatures, and grind the faces of the poore, and they are as ſlaves under you, and muſt labour and toyle under you, and you muſt live at eaſe, ſporting in day time, and ſpending your time in pleaſures,<note place="margin">2 Pet. i2. 13.</note> and Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, and wantonneſs, according to your luſtful minds, in Hauking and Hunting, and bouling &amp; carding, &amp; dicing, in all manner of musick plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure &amp; delights, in eating &amp; drinking and ſleeping, and you muſt have your wine and ale, and all your dainty diſhes, and all manner of delights and novelties, and ſo ye ſeed the luſt; eating and drinking and riſing up to play, which is Idolatry, and you have your fine attire,<note place="margin">1 Cor. i0. 7.</note> and all manner of new faſhions, Silk and velvet, and purple, Gold and Silver, and you have your waiting-men, and waiting-maids under you to wait upon you, and your Coaches to ride, and your high and lofty horſes is like your ſelves, according to your lofty minds, and you sit at eaſe, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves like, devouring the Creation, and ſpending it upon your luſts, and with it committing fornication, into it your hearts being adultred from God, who created you, and your fellow-creatures muſt labour like ſlaves under you, and works for all this, when you are at your pleaſures, they muſt be at work and labour, that muſt Hunger and thirſt and labour, when you are eating, and drinking, and ſleeeping, and here like Dives you sit at eaſe, and poor Lazarus lyes ſtarving without, and here you are Lords over your fellow-Creatures,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.20. 2i.</note> and they muſt bow and crouch to you or elſe they muſt bee hated, and puniſhed, and put out from your preſence, and be ſcoffed, and ſcorned, and reproached, and you wil be called Maſters, and thinks ſcorn that a poore man ſhould ſtand with his hat on before you, and ſo ſets up partiallity, which that Law of God condemns, upholding that which Chriſt in his doctrine forbids, who ſaith, be not ye called Maſters, and ſo by it which you did profeſs,<note place="margin">Mat. 23.8.</note> you are condemned, and you think ſcorn in particular, to be thoued of your
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168077:3"/>
fellow-Creatures, which is the Scripture language to one, but you will thou God and Chriſt, and yet you wil not be thoued, and here you exalt your ſelves above God, and Lords over your fellow-creatures, but though you be exalted as high as the Heavens, and ſet your neſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Stars,<note place="margin">Obad. 3.4,</note> and lay up treaſures for many yeers, thence will the Lord fetch you down, and caſt you into Hell the pit, as he did Lucifer, Dives,<note place="margin">Iſa. i4. 13, i4. i5.</note> and Hammen, and Pharoah, and Herod, and the reſt of your fore fathers, who would have been exalted above the Creator as you would, for it is Lucifer who is head and is exhalted in you, above all that is called God, oppoſing God, who is God over you, whom you ſerve and worſhip, for whom the pit is prepared: To the light in all your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences I ſpeak, which is honeſt of God, and impartial, which wil let you ſee you are guilty and condemn you,<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2, 3, 4.</note> but you think to have the pleaſure and delights of this world, to be at eaſe and peace here, and to have an inheritance in the Kingdome of Good too, and you have covers for all this, you ſay your pleaſures is paſtime and recreation, and your fyne cloathes and gay attire, is comlineſs and decency, and your dainty di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes and banqueting novelties and attendance, you ſay you are able to maintain it, and it belongs to your places, and ſo you have covers for all, but wo unto you that hide your Sins, and covers your iniquities, who covers with a covering but not with the Lord, but all your covers is found too narrow before the Lord Chriſt,<note place="margin">Prov. 28. i3. Iſa. 30.1.</note> who wil lay all your hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſye and deceit before you, and your vain lyes and actions, and you ſhall be rewarded accordingly, and ſhall have your portion in the Lake that burneth, which is prepared for you earth-worms, whoſe pleaſure is in the earth, but you think to be ſaved, and ſo would make Chriſt and his Apoſtles lyars, who ſaid, none could obtaine two Kindomes, and no ſuch muſt enter who have their portions and delight in the earth,<note place="margin">Iames 5. i. 5.</note> and you make a profeſſion of godlines with your praiers, praiſes graces, &amp; ſinging &amp; formal imaginary worſhip, and have a Chaplain or a Prieſt to preach to you one day in a week, and all the week after do as you do, and ſpends the time as you do, in eating, and drinking, and rising up to play, and lives in pride and covetouſneſs, and is called of men Maſter, and you have a place for him to preach to you, in either in your houſes or hard-by, ſo have all things at eaſe, and all this for your money, but the pearl you want,<note place="margin">Iob. 28.</note> which is not to be purchaſed with money, where lies the ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable treaſures: and you ſay he is a Miniſter of Chriſt, and he ſaith you are Chriſtians, whenas you all are Heathens both Prieſt and people, living without God in the world, and ſo the blind leads the blind into the Ditch, and ſo you lead your lives and ſpend your time here and thinks to be ſaved hereafter; no, no, wo, and wo is coming upon you all who are proud, you muſt all give an account before the Lord God, of Heaven and Earth, who is terrible to the wicked, and behold, the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168077:3"/>
day of the Lord cometh, which will burn as an Oven, and all that are proud,<note place="margin">Mal. 4.1. Gal. 6.6, 7, 8.</note> and all that do wickedly ſhall be as ſtubble and ſuch as you ſow ſuch muſt you reap, he that ſows to the fleſh of the fleſh, muſt reap cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, the Lord abhors all your profeſſion, and your hypocriſye, it is not profeſſion that he ſeeks for, it is practiſe, it is not the ſayer, but the doer that ſhall inherit, your forefathers ſaid but did not, ſo do you, but it is not all that ſaith Lord, Lord, that ſhall inherit,<note place="margin">Mat. 7. 2i.</note> but he that doth the will of my Father; what is the chaffe to the wheat? the Lord looks for fruits, you profeſs him in words, but your works are the works of the Devil, and l'o are of this ſort who come neer him with their lips,<note place="margin">Iſa. 29. i3.</note> but their hearts are far from him, in your gay attire, in your new faſhions, in your varieties, in your dainty diſhes, in your Gaming and pleaſures, and ſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, in your wealth and earthly riches, in your lofty horſes, in your cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious buildings, in your fyne Musick, in your earthly honor, which is all the fruits of the Devil, and here outwardly you profeſs the Lord, wth your tongues, but ſerve the Devil with your hearts and actions, who is the King of pride, and here you are in the broad and easie way,<note place="margin">Iames 5.6.</note> in the fyrſt nature, which is in the fall ſeparated from God, whoſe Kingdom is of this world, ſtrangers to the life of God, and are at enmity, ſlaying and crucifying the juſt and innocent, and ſo are no Chriſtians but Heathens both Prieſt and people, and the Lord abhors all ſacrafycers from Cain, which is the fyrſt nature wherein you live, rove out from God into the earth, your lives preacheth you forth, ſo all your graces before and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meat, and your prayers, and your praiſes and Singing, and formall worſhips and traditions, the Lord abhors,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.3.5. Iſa. 1. i2, 13, i4. 15, 16, i7. Prov. i5. 8.</note> for they are offered up in the fyrſt nature, a ſacrifyce of the earth, and Savours of the earth, and is not a ſweet ſmell unto him, and therefore he hath no reſpect to it, his ſoul loaths it, away with it, and they that offer it, for it is enmity with him, the prayers and ſacrifyces of the wicked is abominable, all prayers or Sacrifices offered ap from Cain, Dives or Hammon, or any in that nature, is abominable to the Lord, and he wil not accept them, for to them he hath no reſpect, therefore all you high and lofty ones, Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon like, be ye ſylent and let your mouths, be ſtopped all you who acts in unrighteouſneſs, away with all your profeſſion, and now repent and tremble before the Lord, ye children of the Devil, come down all you high and lofty ones, houl and mourn in ſackcloath and aſhes, for the Lord is coming to burn you up as ſtubble before him, for you are the fruitleſſe TREES that cumbers the ground,<note place="margin">Mat. 27.19.</note> who are for the Fire, faire and flouriſhing with Leaves you are covered, but by CHRIST the LIGHT, ye are ſearched, and no Fruit is ſound on you, therefore from him you are curſed for fruit hee is come to ſeeke for, therefore profeſs him no longer in words, but now repent and return from all your UNRIGHTEOUSNESS,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168077:4"/>
for know you not that no unrighteous perſon ſhall inherit the Kingdom of God,<note place="margin">i Cor. 6.9.</note> no vain perſon nor drunkards, ſwearers, no lyar, no proud, no covetous ones, none who delight in gaming or pleaſures, ſpotting in the day time and riotting, chambering and wantonneſs, nor no unholy nor unclean thing muſt enter, for all unrighteous perſons muſt be caſt into the Lake that burns with Fire and brimſtone for ever: now read your ſelves and your Portions, all you high and lofty ones, for thither you muſt go, and there you muſtly for evermore, the Lord of hoſts hath ſpoke it, with Dives and Hammon, and all the high and lofty ones who muſt be caſt in thither,<note place="margin">Eaſter 3.</note> for you are too high and too Fine, and too lofty to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in at the ſtraight gate, as Dives was, and Hammon was, nay, you are enemeis and perſecutors of all thoſe who enters in at the ſtraite gate, as Hammon, and Dives, and the High Prieſts, Phariſes, and Rulers was, and all the high ones, becauſe they do not feed you with your earthly honour, and reſpects no perſon, but equalizes all fleſh, as the Lord doth ſo doth his people,<note place="margin">Acts i0.34.35.</note> but you proud ones thinks ſcorn to be compared, or to be equalized with your fellow-creatures, as Dives and Hammon did, but all you proud ones, remember your father Dives end, for thither you muſt go into the everlaſting burnings, as he did, whoſe belly was his God,<note place="margin">Luke i6. i9. &amp; Phil. 3. i9.</note> as yours is, whoſe end is deſtruction, who mind earthly things, and then it wil be too late for you to repent, and then when it is too late, then you wil wiſh you had been as Lazarus was, ſo that at the end you might have enjoyed the happineſs that Lazarus did, though now you are exalted above your fellow-creatures,<note place="margin">Ezekiel i6. 44.</note> living in Pride, Idleneſs, and fulneſs of bread, which was the Sins of Sodome, but in this day you ſhal be brought down, and all you workers of eniquity, young and old, rich, and poor, Lord and Lady, and beggars ſhall be all turned into Hel with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of perſon,<note place="margin">Iſaiah 2.42. Heb. i0. 8.34. Heb. 1i. 36, 37, 38. Luke i6. 22.23</note> then ſhall it be with the Miſtriſs, ſo with the maid, as with the Servant ſo with the Maſter, and as with the people, ſo with the Prieſt, &amp; all the righteous ſimple ones which you deſpiſe and ſcoff at, who are now to you gazing ſtocks, and reproaches and pilgrims in the world, becauſe their Kingdom is not of this world, then ſhall that be exalted and received into joy eternal, then you ſhal ſee a ſeparation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the humble and the proud, as there was betwixt Dives and Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, the humble, and loly, and deſpiſed ones ſhall be exalted, and you high lofty ones, who are deſpiſers and crucifyers of the juſt, ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſed and caſt into Hell, then Lord and Lady, Maſter and Miſtris and all your earthly honor, ſhall be laid into the fyre, then all your worldly wealth, riches, and earthly inheritance and heir-ſhips will be gone, wherewith you ruled as Lords in the eerth,, then you ſhall fynd that all your gay cloathing and rich attire was for pride, and not for decency, and that many of your fellow-creatures wanted that for to cover their nakedneſs which you ſpent upon your luſts, then you ſhall be rewarded for grinding the faces of the poor, for your oppreſſions, and for rackings
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168077:4"/>
and taxings and your heavy burthens, wherewith you oppreſs your fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low creatures, for you are the high Oaks and the tall Cedars that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the little ſcrubs under,<note place="margin">Iſa. 2. i2, i3. &amp;c.</note> whom the Creation growns both man and beaſts, but then you will be brought low, then all your pleaſures and wantonneſs, hauking and hunting, and bowling and carding, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing and all your Musik ſhall be turned into weeping and howling with Dives, Lazarus had none of this, but Dives had, but now Lazarus hath joy eternall, and Dives wo and miſery everlaſting, and then all your dainty diſhes and novelties and varieties which hath fed your luſts ſhall be turned into fyre and brimſtone, and the ſpoyle of the creatures ſhall witneſs againſt you, and then you ſhall be ſtript of of all your Silks and Velvet, and Purple, and Gold, and Silks, and all your gay attire, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you decked and addorned your Earthly bodies, to make your ſelves ſeem glorious in the eyes of other, for the honor and eſteem of the world but then you will be as naked as the beggar, then you ſhall have no wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting men nor waiting maids, nor Coaches, nor high and lofty horſes, nor curious building, or great houſes, no more than the beggar, then bowing and crouching, and all your heatheniſh breeding ſhall be laid aside,<note place="margin">Ezek. 22.28. Ier. 13. i. Mich. 3.5.</note> then all your Prieſts &amp; falſe Prophets which you extall now ſo high becauſe they daub you up and cry, peace to you, healing you in deceit, becauſe you put into their mouths, ſhal ſtand you in no ſteed, but ſhall be tormented with you hypocrites in the lake, and all your covers wil not ſerve wherewith you hide your Sin, and covers over your deceipts, in ſaying your pleaſures and vain talk, and fooliſh jeſting, and tales and ſtories, is paſtime and recreation, then you would be glad of one hour if you could get to repent in, as Dives would, but then it will be too late for your portion you enjoy in the earth, whoſe Kingdom is of this world, but the Son of man in it had ſcarce where to lay his head, and his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants no certain dwelling place, for their Kingdom was not of this world, ſuch you call wanderers and vaggabonds, who have your great houſes and ſtrong towers in the Earth, but all cannot hide from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord, who will you call in judgment, and reward you accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your deeds,<note place="margin">Luke 9.5.58. i Cor. 4. ii. Pſalms i45. i3.</note> when his own he doth exalt into the Kingdom which for them he hath prepared, which is an everlaſting Kingdom, from which the earthworms are ſhut out, who ſaith the earth is mime, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now before it be too late conſider of it, and let Dives and Hammon and the reſt of the proud ones be a warning to you, and now repent, while it is called to day, now you have been told, now you are left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excuſe, before the juſt impartial Iudge; now priſe your time all who deſyre mercy at the hand of God, and pardon for your iniquities, for this is the day of your visitation,<note place="margin">Luke i6. i3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> wherein the Lord is handing forth his mercy, and if you will not believe this, you would not blieve Dives and he ſhould riſe from the Dead.</p>
            <p>To the light in all your Conſciences I ſpeak, which comes from Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168077:5"/>
Chriſt the light of the world,<note place="margin">Iohn i. 9.</note> who doth enlighten every one that comes into the world, which light is his witneſs in the conſcience, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all deceit, ungodlineſs, and unrighteouſneſs of men, which light in all your conſciences is my witneſs, to the which I am made manifeſt, which if you love it, and to it hearken, it will let you ſee your ſelves, and the ſtaite and condition wherein you live, and the fylthy unclean Image of the Devill which you bear, and your Leoperous ſpotted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, becauſe of the luſt wherein you are drowned, and the ſame light loving it and following it, which checks and covinces in the conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience, for that which is evil and of the leaſt contrary to the wil of God, it wil lead you to repentance, and humble your hearts, and bring you down to know the fear of the Lord, whoſe power wil rend your habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons wherein you have dwelt ſecure in your Sins, and this light (loving it) will be your teacher, and wil let you ſee the Creation and the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thareof, and will teach you how to uſe it and order it in its place, out of the luſt, to the glory of God, and how to do good with it, ſo that there be no want in the creation nor cry of oppreeſſion, but the hungry wil be fed, and the naked cloathed, and the oppreſſed ſet free, and here is the bleſſing reſtored to the Creation, but while theſe things is under and you live in the luſts, with your abundance, nouriſhing your hearts as in a day of ſlaughter, the curſe is upon you and war abundance, and you are the adulterers and adultereſſes,<note place="margin">Titus. 2. ii. i2. Iames 4. Iames 5.</note> whoſe hearts are adulterated from God, committing fornication with the Creation, and the grace of God which ſhould guide you out of the luſt and ungodlineſs of the world you turn into wantonneſs, and your teachers who cauſe you to erre by their ſorcery and inchantments, and Iames the Son of thunder uttered forth his voice againſt ſuch, and thus ſaith the Lord, becauſe the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Sion are haughty, and walk with ſtretched out necks, and wanton eyes, walking and mincing as they go, and making a tinkling with their feet, therefore the Lord will ſmite with the ſcab the Crown of the head of the Daughters of Sion, in that day in that day the Lord wil take away all their bravery of their tinkling ornaments of their feet,<note place="margin">Iſaiah. 3.</note> and their cauls and round attire, like the Moone, and the chains and the brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, and the head-bands, and tablets, and the Ear-rings, and the noſe-Iewels, the changeables ſuits of apparell, and the mantles, and the wim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and the Criſping-pins, and the glaſſes, and the fyne linnen, and the hoods, and the vails, and it ſhall come to paſs, that inſtead of ſweet ſmel, there ſhall be a ſtinck, and inſtead of well ſeat here, bauldneſs, and idſtead of a ſtomacher, a girding with Sackcloath, and burning in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of beauty: Now all you high and lofty Daughters of England, who are ſporting your ſelves in the day time, and ſcorning and diſdaining your fellow-creatures, read your ſelves and your portions, howle and lament, for a day of venegance, of rending, of burning, of famine, is coming upon you, for the Land mourns becauſe of pride.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:168077:5"/>
            <head>TO THE LIBERTINE, whoſe Liberty ſtands in the Fleſh.</head>
            <p>WOE unto thee, who art at eaſe in the <hi>fleſh,</hi> devouring the <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,</hi> and ſpending it upon thy <hi>Lusts,</hi> whoſe heart is run from <hi>God</hi> awhoring after other Lovers, committing, <hi>Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> with the <hi>Creation,</hi> nouriſhing thy heart as in a day of <hi>ſlaughter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 23.30. Pſal. i0.39. Iames 5.5. Rev, i8.7. Heb. 10.29. Mal. 2. i7.</note> ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying thy <hi>luſts</hi> in whatſoever thy heart runs after, and ſo art at eaſe in the <hi>fleſh,</hi> and feels no <hi>ſorrow</hi> nor <hi>griefe,</hi> but the <hi>Harlot</hi> is exalted in thy <hi>Boſome,</hi> above all that is called <hi>God,</hi> and thou had caſt his <hi>Law</hi> behind thy back, living withoutt the fear of <hi>God</hi> and walking diſpitefully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> ſaying within thy ſelfe, he that doth <hi>evill</hi> is good in the ſight of <hi>God,</hi> and where is the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Iudgment?</hi> can we do any thing without <hi>God,</hi> is it not by his <hi>power</hi> we do all things, and can we do any thing contrary to his <hi>VVill;</hi> yea, thou ſhalt fynde, that all thou doſt is contrary to his <hi>will,</hi> and thou ſhalt fynde him, a <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Iudgment,</hi> for thy <hi>Sins</hi> hath ſeparated thy <hi>Soul</hi> from <hi>God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 59.2.</note> and long in his <hi>love</hi> and <hi>mercy</hi> to thy ſoul hath he forborn thee, and hath not cut thee off from off the face of the earth, but hath ſtill ſpared thee, and waited to be gracious, though thy <hi>heart</hi> hath been wholly gone from him, and never regarded to do that which is pleasing in his sight, but inſtead of ſerving him, thou haſt ſerved thy own <hi>lusts,</hi> with his good <hi>creatures</hi> to which thou haſt had no right, and he to thee hath been a mercifull <hi>God;</hi> but will not the <hi>Lord</hi> visite for theſe things? yea, he wil not always ſtrive with man, and though thou takeſt thy pleaſure now, remember thou muſt come to <hi>Iudgment, And lo ſaith the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 6.3. Eccle. ii. 9. Rev. 22.12. Gal. 6.8.</note> 
               <hi>I come quickly and my reward is with me, to give unto every one according to his deeds. And they that ſow to the fleſh, ſhall of the fleſh reap corruption:</hi> And then thou ſhalt finde that power thou haſt had, and inſtead of using it to the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> thou haſt hid thy <hi>Talent</hi> in the <hi>Earth,</hi> and lived wantonly upon the <hi>Earth,</hi> ſerving thy own will, diſhonouring the <hi>Holy Lord</hi> of <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> and then in the day of thy <hi>Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> thou ſhalt confeſs that the <hi>Lord</hi> hath visited thee time after time, and called thee time after time, handing forth his <hi>Mercy</hi> to thee, when
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168077:6"/>
thou harkned, the <hi>Lord</hi> was with thee, when thou walked in his fear, he was not far from thee, but thou haſt hearkned to the voice of the <hi>Serpent</hi> and falſe <hi>Prophet,</hi> which hath drawn thy heart from God, into the visible things of the <hi>Creation,</hi> which paſs away, and hath promiſed thee <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> in the ſame, and it being pleasing to thy <hi>lustfull earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly minde,</hi> thou art become one with the <hi>Harlot,</hi> which lyeth in thy <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 4, 8.9.</note> and thus thou haſt accepted the gift with which the <hi>Old Serpent</hi> tempted <hi>Christ,</hi> and ſo art become a <hi>Servant</hi> to the <hi>Devill,</hi> of whom thou art brought in <hi>bondage</hi> of him, being evermore, and while thou art pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mising to thy ſelfe <hi>Liberty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. i9, 20, 2i.</note> thou thy ſelfe art a <hi>Servant</hi> unto <hi>corruption;</hi> and thus thy <hi>lusts</hi> hath ſeparated betwixt <hi>God</hi> and thy <hi>Soul,</hi> and art be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the <hi>Image</hi> of the <hi>Devill,</hi> yeilding thy <hi>Members ſervants</hi> to <hi>unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> &amp; thus thou ſets up a reſt in the <hi>Devils Kingdom,</hi> wherin thou ſports thy ſelf and art at liberty,<note place="margin">i Cor. i0, 7. i Cor. i5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8, 9.</note> eating and drinking in merrineſs, ſo if there were ſorrow only in this world, thou art of all men moſt happy, then our Fathers that are faln aſleep in Chriſt are periſhed, and we are of all men moſt miſerable, if there be joy only in this world; but out of the liberty of the children of God thou art found, and by them ſeen to be in the fall, wallowing in the myre and luſt, and ſo art unredeemed, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving under the Curſe,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> for this is the redemption from death to life, and thou liveſt after the fleſh, and art dead, the carnall minde ruling which is death, and is at enmity with God, for it is not ſubject to the will of God, and ſo long as this hath dominion over thee, thou cannot obey God, for he that lives in the fleſh, cannot pleaſe God, but if through the Spirit thou mortify the deeds of the fleſh thou ſhalt live,<note place="margin">Rom. 8. i.</note> and here is the liberty of the Children of God, <hi>VVho walk not after the fleſh but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Spirit,</hi> but their liberty is not in the fleſh, but in the Spirit, for by the law of the Spirit of life they are ſet free from the law of Sin and death: <hi>And from Chriſt their Redeemer, they have received power to become the Sons of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. i, i2.</note> and in the ſame have dominion over the world, fleſh, ſelf, and the Devil, death and Hell, and this comes through the Croſs, by which they are crucifyed to the world and the world to them, and here is the liberty of the Children of God,<note place="margin">Galla. 6. i4.</note> who walk not after the fleſh but after the Spirit, which liberty no vulterous eye can ſee, nor vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous beaſt ſhall know, nor the rebellious diſobedient one, therefore do not deceive thy felfe in ſaying, thou art a Chriſtian and believes in Chriſt, and art a child of God; for they that are Chriſts have crucifyed the fleſh,<note place="margin">Galla. 5.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Romans 6. i6.</note> and to whom thou yeilds thy members ſervants to obey, his ſervant thou art, to the light of God in thy conſcience I ſpeak, which if thou love it and unto it hearken, and bring thy deeds unto it to be tryed by it, it will witneſs for God and his Children, againſt thee to be a Child of the Devil, and his works thou doſt, and thy faith to be feig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned like the Hypocrite, and doth not purifye thy heart and ſo is no more than the wickedeſt that is, for all ſay that Chriſt dyed for them, but all
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168077:6"/>
cannot witneſs it, <hi>For he that believes is born of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.9.</note> and he that is born of God doth not commit Sin, and this light loving it, will let thee ſee how thy heart is turned from God, and that thou haſt more delight in the things that periſh, than in the fear of the living God, which keeps the heart clean, <hi>And is the beginning of the pure wiſdome and righteouſneſs,</hi> and if thou honeſtly commune with it,<note place="margin">Prov. 9. i0.</note> it will let thee ſee thy ſecret a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and all thy hidden deeds done in darkneſs, that thou maiſt come to judgment, and condemnation for all theſe things, and except thou be born again and become as a little Child, thou art no child of God, neither can enter the Kingdome of God, but art without in the worlds nature, in the ſtate of condemnation, in whom the Son of perdition rules above all that is called God, Sitting in the Temple of God, as God, and ſaith he is God, and here he oppoſeth God in his Kingdom, and ſaith that is lawfull, and for it pleads which God ſaith is unlawfull and forbids, and he tels the Creature and makes it believe it cannot keep Gods Commandments, and that it hath not power to do that which God commands it, or to depart from evill, and that none lives but they Sin, and Chriſt hath ſatisfyed for all Sin, though they Sin day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; that man may uſe the Creatures as hee pleaſeth, ſeeing they were made for mans uſe, and the Spirit of God ſaith, he that ſaith he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God and keepeth not his commandments,<note place="margin">i Ioh. 2.4. i Iohn i. i2. Romans 8.2.</note> is a lyar and the truth is not in him; <hi>And as many as receives him, to them he gives power to become the Sons of God; And the Law of the Spirit of life, makes them free from the Law of Sin and death, He that commits ſin is of the Devill and never knew God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">i Ioh 3. Romans 8. Hebrews i2. i4.</note> 
               <hi>and by this are the Children of God and the Children of the Devill made manifest and he that abides in him ſinneth not; And he that lives after the fleſh cannot pleaſe God, for without holineſs none ſhall ſee the Lord:</hi> and thus the Devill the Old Serpent who was a lyar from the beginning, oppoſeth God in his Kingdom, daubing the Creature up in that vvhich is evil, making it a habitation in his Kingdome, vvhile it lives upon the earth, and then muſt take part with him in the lake that is prepared for the Devill and his Servants, who doth not dare to call God a hard Maſter, as if he would lay a tax upon the Creature which it is not able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, and thus he deceives the Creature, and draws out of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God, and out of the fear of God, which preſerves from evill, and ſo he draws into careleſneſs and ſlothfulneſs,<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.5.6</note> and begets a liberty therein, and becauſe of thoſe things commeth the wrath of God upon the Children of diſobedience, as it was in the beginning when God ſaid that in the day thou eats of the Apple thou ſhalt die the death, and the Serpent ſaid, you ſhall not ſurely dye, for God doth know that in the day you eat thereof, you ſhall be as Gods, knowing Good and Evill,<note place="margin">Gen.</note> and thus he deceived them, and drew them out of the commands of God and out of the feaſt of God into the diſobedience, and ſo came the curſe of God upon them, by hearkning to him, and entring into his tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168077:7"/>
and then they found God juſt and true, and the Devil a lyar, whom they had believed; now read thy ſelf, to the light of Chriſt in thy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience I ſpeak, which ſearcheth the heart, and knows the ſecret thoughts and intents of the heart, which will witneſs me, and condemn thee who walks contrary unto it, be not deceived, God is not mocked, <hi>for ſuch as thou ſoweſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.7</note> 
               <hi>ſuch muſt thou reap,</hi> for God is a juſt God, and wil not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit the wicked, for thou art found a ſloathful ſervant, who hath hid thy talent in the earth, and think not that thou ſhalt receive the reward of the righteous and faithfull, for if the righteous ſcarcely be ſaved, what will become of the wicked and ungodly, therefore repent while its cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to day,<note place="margin">i Pet. 4. i8,</note> harden not thy heart, leaſt the judgments of God come upon thee at unawares and ſweep thee away, and give thee thy portion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ſloathfull hypocrites and unbelievers, for by the light of God thou art ſeen and found in the Sins of Sodom, and the plagues of Sodom is comming upon thee, therefore be afflicted and mourn, and let thy laughter be turned to mourning and thy joy into heavineſs, for to judgment thou muſt come,<note place="margin">Iam. 4.9.</note> and thy liberty; to the light of Chriſt in thy conſcience I am made manifeſt, which if thou loves it, will let thee ſee thy ſelf, and tender thy conſcience and wil lead thee into the fear of God following of it, and will humble thee, and bring down thy high and lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty looks, and bring thee under judgment and condemnation for thy ſtiff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neckedneſs, diſobedience, and rebellion againſt the Son of righteouſneſs, here will be thy condemnation, out of thy own mouth wil the Lord judg thee in righteouſneſs by the light in thy Conſcience, which he hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned the withall, which now thou Kickeſt againſt, which will thy thy torment be, this is a warning from the Lord unto thee, and now thou art left without excuſe in the preſence of the living God, by the light of God, this is the day of thy visitation, and the day of thy judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment draw nigh, now thou haſt time priſe it: <hi>For the day of the Lord will be as a Thiefe in the night,</hi>
               <note place="margin">i Theſ. 5.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>to all the children of darkneſs, as it was to the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites, and verily I ſay unto thee, it ſhall be more tolerable for</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Gomorah <hi>in the day of Iudgment than for thee, if thou dost not repent, who haſt taſted of the love and mercy of God, and haſt trampled it under foot, and haſt rebelled againſt the Spirit of Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVritten from the Spirit of the Lord, as a warning to all who are in the fleſhly liberty, by a witneſs of the true liberty of the children of God through death, which liberty ſtands not in time, nor in any thing in time for all things in time periſh with time, but this remains when time ſhall be no more, and this is pure unſpotted of the world.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>IAMES PARNEL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="ii" facs="tcp:168077:7"/>
            <p>ALL you that ſcoff, and ſcorn, reproach, &amp; revile at the <hi>Children, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> and <hi>Meſſengers</hi> of the <hi>moſt High God,</hi> whom you nick-name <hi>quakers,</hi> and under the ſame name perſecute them, as a people not worthy to live, and have no ground for it, neither knows any evill by them, but all along their lives and converſations condemns yours, and therefore you hate them, revile them, &amp; reproach them in whom the power of the living God is made manifeſt, the ſame which ever was, <hi>VVhich ſhakes the Earth and makes the ſtrong man to bow himſelf,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. i2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>and the keepers of the houſe to tremble;</hi> and the ſame power which all the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in all ages witneſſed, and paſſed through, which then by the ſame <hi>Generation</hi> ſuffered, both by <hi>Magistrates, Profeſſors, Priests,</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> who were, &amp; are <hi>ſtrangers</hi> to the life of <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Power,</hi> and therfore <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached, Scoffed</hi> and <hi>ſcorned</hi> it, as you now do,<note place="margin">2 Tim 3.3.</note> but it is that the <hi>Scripture</hi> might be fulfilled upon you, <hi>VVho are deſpiſers of thoſe that do good; I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaak the ſeed of the promiſe trembled, Gen.</hi> 27.33. <hi>VVho was mocked by Iſhmael the Son of the Bondwoman, who was cast out as the ſame ſeed;</hi> and now by you <hi>Iſhmalites</hi> who are the Children of the <hi>Bondwoman,</hi> who are caſt out and are found without, mocking and ſcoffing the Righteous ſeed, Gen. 21.9. i0. Gal. 4.30. <hi>And Moſes a Servant of God quaked and trembled, who counted it greater Riches to ſuffer affliction with the people of God, than to enjoy the pleaſures of Sin for a ſeaſon, Heb.</hi> 12. 2i. <hi>Heb.</hi> ii. 26. and this you now call madneſs and folly, <hi>who know not that godlineſs is great gaine,</hi> i <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.6. and <hi>David</hi> who was a King quaked, and trembled, and roared, and watered his Couch with tears, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69. i2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.6. and <hi>Drunkards</hi> made a Song on him, and ſome ſhut out their tongues, and wagged their heads and gaped upon him with their mouths, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 64. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.7. and this you Sing in your Steeple houſes like Hypocrites without knowledg, <hi>Pſalms</hi> 35. i6. and yet ſcoffe and ſcorn and reproach thoſe in whom the ſame Power is made manifeſt and yet you will ſay as he ſaid, <hi>you are not puffed in mind, nor have no ſcornfull eye, &amp;c.</hi> but he ſpoke the truth, and you lye, <hi>Pſal.</hi> i31.1. and thus you deceive your ſouls and loves to have it ſo, your leaders cauſe you to erre, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.16. and <hi>Iob</hi> a Servant of the <hi>Lord</hi> quaked, who by the ſame generation was laughed to ſcorn, <hi>Iob</hi> 4. i4. <hi>Iob</hi> i2. i4. and <hi>Ieremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> a Prophet of the Lord quaked, who was then perſecuted by the ſame <hi>generation Ier.</hi> 23.9. and <hi>Daniel</hi> a <hi>Prophet</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> trembled, who was caſt into the <hi>Lyons Den,</hi> becauſe he would not deny his <hi>God, Dan.</hi> i0, ii. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.16. but by his power he was preſerved, as we are now from thoſe <hi>Lyons whelps</hi> who would us devour; and <hi>Habbkkauk</hi> a Prophet of the Lord his belly trembled, and his lips quivered, <hi>Hab.</hi> 3. i6. and <hi>Paul</hi> an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of Ieſus Chriſt fell down and trembled, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.4.5.6. who was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viled, reproached, and perſecuted even to death, who was one that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarded his life for the name of Ieſus, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.26. and ſaid all the day long was they killed, and accounted as ſheep to the ſlaughter, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.36.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168077:8"/>
now theſe was all quakers, who then ſuffered with patience by the ſame generation, now read what generation you are of, for they that were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſh allways perſecuted them that were after the Spirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.29. there was always a generation by which the righteous ever ſuffered ſince Cain the fyrſt born upon earth, in whoſe way you are found, who envy, who are in the wrath, <hi>Iude</hi> 10. you kill the juſt, and he lyes ſlain in the ſtreets, <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.5, 6. at whoſe hands his blood ſhal be requited. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.35. and the Son of man was to eat his bread with quaking, and drink his water with trembling, <hi>Ezek.</hi> i2. i0. out of which life you are found, who are at eaſe in the fleſh, feeding without the fear of God, ſpending the Creatures upon your luſts, i <hi>Cor.</hi> i0.7. <hi>Iam.</hi> 5 ſcoffing and ſcorning them who are not one with you in the ſame liberty, but fears before the Throne of God, i <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> i3, i4. i <hi>Cor.</hi> i0.3i. and thus you erre, not knowing the Scriptures nor the power of God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.29. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore behold, ye deſpiſers and wonderers, and periſh, I will work a work in your days, which though you ſee it, you ſhall not believe it, <hi>Act.</hi> i3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i. is it not apparent before your eyes, the wicked man returns from his wickedneſs, and the ungodly from his ungodlineſs and the drunkard from his drunkenneſs, and the prophane one from his prophainneſs, and now ſeeks after God, and feare his powerfull name, and this you ſee and cannot believe, but deſpiſes, ſcoffs &amp; ſcorns the power by which this work is done, for it is no new thing but the ſame which was and are, you are in the ſame adulterous generation, which cannot ſee the Signes which follow the truth, <hi>Mat.</hi> i6.3, 4. from whom the Goſpel is hid, whoſe eye is darkned with the God of the world, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3, 4. and ſo ſpeaks evil of the things you know not, <hi>Iude</hi> ii. putting darkneſs for light, and light for darkneſs, evill for good, and good for evill, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.20. you are the ſcoffers that the Apoſtle fore-told of to be in the laſt times, <hi>Iude,</hi> i8. who are deſpiſers of thoſe that are good, incontinent, fierce, Traitor, heady, high minded, lovers of pleaſures more than lovers of God, having a form of godlineſs, but deny the life and powers, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.3, 4, 5. and here you are both Prieſts, people, and profeſſors, who are ſcoffing and ſcorning, ſlandring, reproach, reviling, and perſecuting the righteous innocent ſervants and meſſengers of the moſt high God, who is uttering forth his voyce through them in power, againſt all ungodlineſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs of men, who will you call to judgment, and convince you of all your ungodly deeds, and all your hard ſpeeches, which you have wrongfully ſpoken againſt him and his power, and will reward you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, <hi>Iude</hi> i4, i5. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.2i. Therefore to that which is of God in all your conſciences I ſpeak, which is my witneſs againſt your ungodly lives, which turning your minds to it, and unto it taking heed, will let you ſee you ſpeak evill of the things you know not, loving darkneſs ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than light, becauſe your deeds are evill, <hi>Iob.</hi> 3. i9. therefore fear the Lord God and repent, and take heed of mocking, leaſt your bonds
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168077:8"/>
be made ſtrong. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.22. for God will not be mocked, ſuch as you ſowe, ſuch muſt you reap, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.7. therefore fear before the Lord, and try all things, and hold faſt that which is good, i <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.2i. and deſpiſe nothing before you know it, leaſt you ſpeak evill of Gods elect, for it is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God, <hi>Heb.</hi> i0.3i. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take this for a warning, as from the mouth of the Lord, for no ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance is to be pleaded before the throne of God.</p>
            <p>This was given forth in vindication of the power of God, which is now ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſting in his Sons and Daughters, leaſt the ſimple who are not yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with it, ſhould ſtumble at the name.</p>
            <p>By a friend of the truth and a lover of theſe people, which you who are out of the truth ſcornfully call quakers, but the ſcorners God will judge, and the righteous God will bleſs who work out their ſalvation with fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, for ſaith the Lord, to ſuch a one wil I look, that is of a humble and contrite ſpirit, and trembleth at my words, <hi>Pro. i9.29. Phil. 2. i2 Iſa. 66. i, 2.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>IAMES PARNEL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
